Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is מכות Makkos י"ג,
Yud Gimmel, מכות Makkos 13. We pick up on י"ב עמוד ב',
Yud Beis Amud Beis, about a third of the way from the
bottom, 12b, the משנה Mishnah of the first of the two משניות
Mishnayos wrapping up the idea of ערי מקלט Arei Miklat and somebody
who kills בשוגג. beshogeg. And the משנה Mishnah says the following: הרג
באותה העיר. Harag be'oso ha'ir. Let's say this person that was already
killed בשוגג beshogeg and was exiled to an עיר מקלט, ir miklat,
now killed somebody else in that same city. So what would the
הלכה halacha be? So גולה משכונה לשכונה. goleh mishchuna lishchuna. He have
to exile himself from the neighborhood he's been living in and move
to another neighborhood. He can't go to another עיר מקלט ir miklat
because he's not allowed to leave the עיר מקלט ir miklat that
he's in. But he now has to be in exile, so his
exile is that he's now limited to a specific—he leaves the neighborhood
he's in, he's limited to a specific neighborhood within that עיר מקלט.
ir miklat. Interesting question, right? Because if he would leave the neighborhood
he's exiled to, would he expose himself to being killed by the
גואל הדם goel hadam of the second murder? Presumably not, he's still
in an עיר מקלט. ir miklat. So here we have actually a
distinction that he could violate the terms of his exile but not
actually expose himself by remaining in the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. But
what else can you do? That's what you do. Now let's say
somebody actually was not a murderer but living in the עיר מקלט.
ir miklat. What would happen then? So that's the next part of
the משנה. Mishnah. ובן לוי גולה מעיר לעיר. U'ven Levi goleh me'ir
le'ir. If a לוי, Levi, you know because all the ערי לויים
arei Levi'im serve as ערי מקלט, arei miklat, so he
actually killed somebody accidentally, then
he would be exiled to another city. He would leave one עיר,
ir, one of the ערי לויים arei Levi'im and go to another
one of the ערי לויים arei Levi'im because, you know, like a
normal person who killed, this city is not his עיר מקלט, ir
miklat, he's not yet in exile. So he has to be exiled
to another עיר מקלט. ir miklat. But for the murderer who was
already in or the person who killed, the manslayer who was already
in that city, there's no way to leave that city. Okay, that's
what the משנה Mishnah says. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. תנו רבנן. Tano rabanan. ושמתי לך מקום. Vesamti lecha makom. I
will give you a place that the somebody who kills בשוגג beshogeg
can run there. That's already way back in שמות. Shemos. And the
דרשה derasha is: ושמתי לך בחייך. Vesamti lecha bechayecha.
You משה, Moshe, in your life, this will already happen. This was
before they got to עבר הירדן, Ever HaYarden, was right after יציאת
מצרים, Yetzias Mitzrayim, and God is saying I will give to you
משה Moshe a place, you will see it in your own life.
And that was presaging the three ערי מקלט arei miklat in עבר
הירדן. Ever HaYarden. מקום Makom or לך מקום, lecha makom, ממקומך. mimkomecha.
It'll be from among your places, from the ערי לויים. arei Levi'im.
So that's another דרשה derasha of juxtaposing the לך lecha and the
מקום, makom, so the ערי מקלט arei miklat will be designated from
among the ערי לויים. arei Levi'im. And all the ערי לויים arei
Levi'im can function as ערי מקלט. arei miklat. אשר ינוס שמה, Asher
yanus shama,
that he will run there. מלמד שהיו שם גולים במדבר. Melamed shehayu
sham galim bamidbar.
That this would already apply even when they were in the wilderness,
even before the ערי מקלט arei miklat had been designated. Not exactly
clear how the גמרא Gemara is learning that from the פסוק pasuk
that it was already
active, but that's what the ברייתא beraisa is saying. Somehow we see
the פסוק pasuk indicates it was immediately active. Okay, so where would
they go if there weren't ערי מקלט? arei miklat? להיכן מגלין? Leheicha
maglin? Where would they go? למחנה לויה. Lemachaneh Leviyah. To the Levite
camp. If ערי מקלט arei miklat were going to be from the
ערי לויים arei Levi'im and all the ערי לויים arei Levi'im could
function as ערי מקלט, arei miklat, so מחנה לויה machaneh Leviyah functioned
as an עיר מקלט ir miklat in the מדבר. midbar. מכאן אמרו
בן לוי שהרג גולה מפלך לפלך. Mikan amru ben Levi sheharag goleh
mipelech lepelech.
From here they said that if a בן לוי ben Levi kills,
he would have to exile himself from his city
to another one. Now it's not clear how you learn that at
all from the פסוק, pasuk, that's just logical. What are you going
to do with a בן לוי ben Levi who killed? Okay, go
to exile and go to a different עיר מקלט. ir miklat. But
it really seems מכאן אמרו mikan amru is the second part of
this: ואם גולה לפלכו פלכו קולטו. Ve'im gola lepelcho pelcho kolto.
But if however he exiles himself within his own city, then his
own city can serve as his עיר מקלט. ir miklat. Now what
does that exactly mean? Like if I don't have to leave my
city, then why should I go to another city? And where do
you learn this from? So תוספות Tosafos says this second part of
this ברייתא beraisa means that actually he can opt, like the case
of the רוצח rotze'ach in the first part of the משנה, Mishnah,
he can opt to exile himself within his city to another neighborhood.
So the person who already is in an עיר מקלט ir miklat
because he killed somebody, he has no choice but to exile himself
to another neighborhood. A
בן לוי ben Levi or somebody who happens to be living in
an
עיר מקלט ir miklat but only now has killed someone can either
go to a different עיר מקלט ir miklat or can stay within
the one he's in but exile himself to another neighborhood. Why would
you opt for the first if you could stay within the same
city? Well the answer's obvious, that I could stay within the same
city but I'm limited to a very small neighborhood, I can never
leave that neighborhood, whereas if I would actually go to a totally
different city I would be able to freely circulate totally within the
city. So you have that so somebody who kills in an עיר
מקלט Ir Miklat and this is the first time he killed somebody
would have that choice. And that seems to be what the מכאן
אמרו Mikan Amru is saying that since there was only one מחנה
לוייה Machaneh Leviyah in the מדבר, Midbar, you have to see it
has to be possible for a scenario what would happen if a
בן לוי Ben Levi would kill when he was in the מדבר?
Midbar? He would have to be from here you see that you
can exile yourself that exile can take place within the same city
because that was the only thing that could have happened in the
מדבר Midbar if a בן לוי Ben Levi killed someone. Okay. אמר
רב אחא בריה דרב איקא מאי קרא, Amar Rav Aha Brei DeRav
Ika Mai Kra, what's the פסוק? pasuk? כי בעיר מקלטו ישב, Ki
Be'Ir Miklato Yeshev, עיר שקלטתו כבר. Ir Shekaltoso Kevar. In the city
of his מקלט Miklat he shall dwell, even a city that has
already sort of absorbed him and protected him, that could remain his
city of exile. That actually seems to be going back on, you
know, the case about somebody that not not just the בן לוי
Ben Levi that's הרוג, harog, but somebody that already committed a killed
somebody and the city has already absorbed him, he that city can
also continue to serve as an עיר מקלט. Ir Miklat. Okay, that's
already a different חידוש chiddush than the בן לוי. Ben Levi. This
is this is somebody that's already functioning as an עיר מקלט Ir
Miklat can now function again. All right. Next משנה. Mishna. כיוצא בו.
Kayotzei Bo. Now, similar, now this similar is actually not similar at
all to the previous משנה. Mishna. This is just a transcription from
a משנה Mishna in שביעית. Shevi'is. If you take a look you
see inside it's from the tenth פרק perek of שביעית Shevi'is because
in in that פרק perek the previous משנה Mishna said that, you
know, שמיטה Shemitah annuls the debts and if somebody, you know, comes
and says, what do you call it,
you know, here I want to pay back my money and you
say, no, no, you know, you don't have to, שמיטה Shemitah annulled
it, you know, and he can say, no, no, no, nevertheless I
still want to pay it back. Okay and so here's what the
משנה Mishna says, this is פרק י' משנה ח' perek yud mishna
chet in שביעית. Shevi'is. המחזיר חוב בשביעית, Hamachazir Chov Bashevi'is, יאמר לו
משמט אני. yomar lo meshamet ani.
Somebody comes to return your debt, you say, no, I annul it.
אני משמט. Ani meshamet. אמר לו, Amar lo, אף על פי כן,
af al pi chen, nevertheless,
I still want to give it back, I still want to pay
you, even though I know you're annulling it. יקבל מהן, Yekabel mehen,
then you can accept it from him. שנאמר וזה דבר השמיטה. shene'emar
vezeh devar hashemitah.
This is the matter of the שמיטה. shemitah. But it's learning from
the word דבר devar that that you know that you say the
words that just speaking the words that that
you say the words I am משמט. meshamet. Okay and it teaches
you it's important to actually say those words. And maybe also what
you're learning is that once you say those words and you've checked
that box, the person can then give you back the money, you
know, as well and it's elsewhere explained that that teaches I'm giving
it to you as a gift, not as paying off a loan
and you've done what you needed to do by saying the words
I'm משמט. meshamet. Okay, so וזה דבר השמיטה. vezeh devar hashemitah. And
then the משנה mishna in שביעית Shevi'is continues and we have the
transcription here. כיוצא בו רוצח. Kayotzei Bo Rotze'ach. Similarly, a רוצח rotze'ach
that גלו לעיר מקלטו, galu le'ir miklato, a רוצח, rotze'ach, you know,
somebody that was sent to an עיר מקלט, Ir Miklat, ורצו אנשי
העיר לכבדו veratzu anshei ha'ir lechabdo and they wanted to honor him,
יאמר להם רוצח אני, yomar lahem rotze'ach ani, I am a murderer,
I can't accept that honor. אמרו לו אף על פי כן, Amru
lo af al pi chen, nevertheless,
just like the guy said nevertheless I want to pay you back
your debt. יקבל מהן, Yekabel mehen,
the person can receive the honor the same way the creditor can
receive the money. שנאמר וזה דבר הרוצח. Shene'emar vezeh devar harotze'ach. These
are the words of the רוצח. rotze'ach. Okay, so דבר devar means
you say I'm a רוצח, rotze'ach, וזה דבר השמיטה vezeh devar hashemitah
you say I'm משמט. meshamet. You say I'm a רוצח, rotze'ach, you
have to do that job of saying no, no, not me. And
then if they nevertheless proceed to give back the money, to offer
you an honor, then you are allowed to accept. Okay, top of
י"ג עמוד א'. yud gimmel amud aleph. מעלים היו שכר ללויים, Ma'alim
hayu sachar laleviyim, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehudah.
So the you know the people that would live in the ערי
מקלט, arei miklat, so okay you'd be exiled there, do you get
free room and board? So no, you'd have to actually pay for
your apartment and your pay for your house. You have to live
there but you don't get free room and board. Okay.
Where
and you know תוספות Tosfos says it's not just about רש"י Rashi
תוספות Tosfos have a slight different explanation, anyway it's not just rent
it's also paying just you know property taxes, any taxes that apply
to the people of the city. You have full financial responsibility just
because you're exiled there doesn't get you off of that. דברי רבי
יהודה, Divrei Rabbi Yehudah, that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says. רבי
מאיר אומר לא היו מעלים להם שכר. Rabbi Meir omer lo hayu
ma'alim lahem sachar. No, they would you would not pay rent, you
would not pay anything, sort of like you go to prison, you
know, you don't pay for being in prison. וחוזר לשררה שהיה בה,
Vachozer leserara shehayah bah, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. Now,
if he returns afterwards, this is like a little non sequitur but
maybe going back to the idea before that they wanted to honor
you, so that's at least some similar idea, if you return back,
the person now the כהן גדול kohen gadol dies, he goes back
to his original city, you know, where he was living, he's allowed
to reclaim his past honors. Whole interesting question, so people that go
to prison, serve the time, and then they come back out,
how do we as a community treat them? So here the Rabbi
Meir says the person can assume his previous honors. דברי רבי מאיר.
Divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה אומר לא היה חוזר לשררה שהיה בה.
Rabbi Yehuda omer, Lo haya chozer lisrarah shehayah bah. No,
we do not return him to his previous status. So let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב כהנא מחלוקת בשש. Amar
Rav Kahana, Machlokes beshesh. The debate here about whether you have to
pay taxes or rent or whatever is in the six primary ערי
מקלט. Arei Miklat. אבל דמר סבר לכם. Aval demar savar lachem. You
know, the פסוק pasuk says that והיו לכם הערים, v'hayu lachem ha'arim,
it will be for you, for you the murderers or killers, these
cities will be for refuge. לכם לכל צרכיכם, Lachem, lechol tzarcheichem,
that they're there to serve you in the sense like, you know,
you don't have to pay room and board. I mean, you know,
it's you're imprisoned to a certain degree, but you know, but you
get this benefit that that's the community's responsibility, not your responsibility to
pay for the cost. לכל צרכיכם. Lechol tzarcheichem. Excuse me, I skipped
a line. דמר סבר לכם לקליטה. Demar savar lachem leklita. The first
one holds, or actually Rabbi Yehuda holds...
you know, Rabbi Yehuda holds that לכם lachem means it'll be there
to protect you, but not that you don't have to pay taxes
and pay expenses. ומר סבר לכם לכל צרכיכם. Umar savar lachem lechol
tzarcheichem.
No, it's totally there for you and there are no costs to
you, at least for you know, for rent and so on. אבל
בארבעים ושתיים דברי הכל היו מעלים להם שכר. Aval b'arbayim veshtayim divrei
hakol hayu ma'alim lahem sachar. But for the other 42 which were
not primary ערי מקלט, Arei Miklat, everybody agrees that you would have
to pay for your rent and pay taxes. אמר ליה רבא Amar
lei Rava said, הודאי לכם לכל צרכיכם משמע. Havadai lachem lechol tzarcheichem
mashma. It's an interesting retort of Rava. Rava says what do you
mean? והיו לכם, V'hayu lachem, לכם lachem means that they're yours, they're
at your disposal. Okay, so for all you need, so you don't...
certainly for the six, everybody would agree you don't pay rent, you
don't pay taxes. אלא אמר רבא מחלוקת בארבעים ושתיים. Ela amar Rava
machlokes b'arbayim veshtayim. So the only debate is the remaining 42. דמר
סבר ועליהם תתנו, Demar savar ve'aleihem titnu, of those six you should
give, you know, another 42. כהני לקליטה. Kehanei liklita. So just like
the first six are to absorb and refuge, the next 42 are
for refuge. ומר סבר ועליהם תתנו, Umar savar ve'aleihem titnu,
but only for the function of being refuge, not complete equality. ומר
סבר, Umar savar, and the other opinion that says that they would
not pay rent even on the other 42 according to this way
of framing the debate, ועליהם תתנו כהני, ve'aleihem titnu kehanei, just like
the original six. מה הני לכל צרכיכם אף הני נמי לכל צרכיכם.
Ma haneilechol tzarcheichem, af hani nami lechol tzarcheichem. So if the original
six are for all of your needs, those who killed people, that
you don't have to pay any costs in terms of taxes or
rent, the same is true about the remaining 42. אבל בשש דברי
הכל לא היו מעלים להם שכר. Aval beshesh divrei hakol lo hayu
ma'alim lahem sachar. But for the original six, everybody agreed that they
would not pay rent. So again, I don't know if that's פשט
pshat in the משנה, Mishnah, but Rava takes it for granted that
the debate could not be about the original six and frames the
משנה Mishnah therefore only about the remaining 42. חוזר לשררה שהיה בה.
Chozer lisrarah shehayah bah. Would he go back to the original status?
Okay, so Rabbi Meir says yes,
and you know, again, Rabbi Meir in both cases, it's interesting, it
switches the order, whether Rabbi Meir first or Rabbi Yehuda first, but
in both cases, Rabbi Meir goes easier on the person. He says
that they would not have to pay rent and they could get
back to their original status. And Rabbi Yehuda says they do have
to pay rent and they don't get back to their original status.
תנו רבנן ושב אל משפחתו ואל אחוזת אבותיו ישוב. Tanu rabbanan: Veshav
el mishpachto ve'el achuzat avotav yashuv. He shall return to his family
and to
the inheritance of his fathers. Now, this is not about somebody who
committed murder, this is about somebody who was an עבד עברי eved
Ivri and then it became the יובל. Yovel. Okay, so it says
ישוב. yashuv. למשפחתו
שב. Lemishpachto shav. He returns to his family. ואינו שב למה שהחזיקו
אבותיו דברי רבי יהודה. Ve'eno shav lema shehecheziku avotav, divrei Rabbi Yehuda.
But he doesn't get back the status and the stature that he
had, you know, because in terms of the family status that he
had held before this. You went ahead, you sold yourself as a
slave, that sort of stays with you. You don't totally get back
the status that you had, okay,
presumably also referring to some type of like inherited post. רבי מאיר
אומר אף הוא שב למה שהחזיקו אבותיו. Rabbi Meir omer: Af hu
shav lema shehecheziku avotav. No,
he even goes back to what the status he had, his inherited
post. אל אחוזת אבותיו כאבותיו. El achuzat avotav ke'avotav.
To the inheritance of the fathers just like his fathers, whatever posts
they held, whatever status they had, he's entitled to go back to
that status. He really believes in more full rehabilitation. כיוצא בו וכן
בגולה. Ke'yozeh bo, vechein begola. And then similarly when it comes to
exile,
כשהוא אומר, keshehu omer, when the פסוק pasuk says
ישוב, yashuv, he shall return, right, just so... Because the Braisa we
taught in the Braisa ישוב הרוצח אל ארץ אחוזתו, yashuv harotzeach el
eretz achuzato, he shall return to his land. And it doesn't say
אחוזת אבותיו, achuzat avotav, so where do you get the idea of
the previous, of the status that he held
according to
Rebbi Meir? So לארץ אחוזתו ישוב אינו שב למה שהחזיקו אבותיו, l'eretz
achuzato yashuv eino shav lema shehecheziku avotav, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi
Yehuda. Rabbi Yehuda says
he just goes back to the land, he does not go back
to the status that he had prior to this. רבי מאיר אומר,
Rabbi Meir omer, אף הוא שב למה שהחזיקו אבותיו. af hu shav
lema shehecheziku avotav. No,
he also goes back to what he had, you know, to the
status held by his his family. How do you get that from
the פסוק? pasuk? It just says ארץ אחוזתו. eretz achuzato. So גמר
שיבה שיבה מהתם, gamar shiva shiva mehatam,
because just right there it said ועל אחוזת אבותיו ישוב. ve'al achuzat
avotav yashuv. So that's why that previous Braisa said ישוב וכן ברוצח,
yashuv vechen berotzeach, that ישוב yashuv that it says by the עבד
עברי eved Ivri and by שמיטה shemita links to ישוב הרוצח yashuv
harotzeach
and it tells you the same way the עבד עברי eved Ivri
returns אל אחוזת אבותיו el achuzat avotav to the status that his
forefathers held, same is true here by the רוצח rotzeach according to
Rebbi Meir, he returns to the status his forefathers held. Very interesting
real belief in the sort of rehabilitation.
הדרן עלך אלו הן הגולין. hadran alach elu hein hagolin. So that
is the end of that פרק perek about גלות. galus. ואלו הן
הלוקין, ve'elu hein halokin, and the following are those that get מלקות.
malkus. Now it's a little funny, you know, like what's the what
is the, I mean this whole next פרק perek is going to
deal with חייבי מלקות. chayvei malkus. You know, what exactly is the
segue here, the juxtaposition? So you could understand like סנהדרין Sanhedrin ended
and מכות Makkos is an extension of סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. סנהדרין Sanhedrin ended
with a all about what do you call it, all about חייבי
מיתות. chayvei misos. So what are the other punishments that בית דין
beis din imposes other than getting, you know, מיתה? misa? So one
is exile, גלות, galus, that's obviously in a way it's not physical
and bodily corporal punishment, but it is for, you know, killing somebody.
So that's obviously very, very weighty and the person could get killed
by the גואל הדם. goel hadam. And then after we deal with
exile, you know, we move on to those who get מלקות malkus
and that's, you know, and then that's this פרק. perek. The other
of course, and then עדים זוממים edim zomemim sort of just got
somehow stuck in the middle a little bit. But you know, it's
also interesting to note that these two פרקים, prakim, the second and
the third פרק, perek, the one about גלות galus and the one
about מלקות, malkus, echo the opening of the first פרק. perek. Because
the first פרק perek is what happens, somebody says בן גרושה או
בן חלוצה, ben gerusha o ben chaluza, they don't become a בן
גרושה או בן חלוצה, ben gerusha o ben chaluza, they get מלקות.
malkus. Somebody said this guy's חייב גלות, chayav galus, he doesn't get
גלות, galus, he gets מלקות. malkus. So the משנה mishna opened with
מלקות malkus and גלות galus and sort of set up, you know,
these next the second and the third פרקים prakim about גלות galus
and מלקות. malkus. So now we get on to the third פרק
perek about מלקות. malkus. ואלו הן הלוקין. ve'elu hein halokin. So the
following are people that get מלקות. malkus. Now basically it's anybody who
transgresses a לא תעשה lo ta'aseh that you don't, you know, there's
some exceptions, whether it has to be a לא תעשה שיש בו
מעשה, lo ta'aseh sheyesh bo ma'aseh, there has to be an act
involved, it can't be ניתק לעשה, nitak l'aseh, it can't have an
עשה aseh connected to it that would fix it. But there's a
large number, I mean there's 365 לא תעשה'ס, lo ta'asehs, so that's
a heck of a lot of people that are getting מלקות. malkus.
Also wouldn't be somebody that would get מיתה misa for for a
לא תעשה lo ta'aseh because then, you know, the מיתה misa is
the punishment. But other than that, it's pretty much, you know, a
large, large number. We're not going to list all of them. But
we're going to list those that there is some חידוש chiddush about.
So let's take a look.
The first set is people that would get כרת. kares. הבא על
אחותו, haba al achoto, somebody who has intercourse a man who has
intercourse with his sister, ועל אחות אביו, ve'al achot aviv, his father's
sister, ועל אחות אמו, ve'al achot imo, his mother's sister, ועל אחות
אשתו, ve'al achot ishto, his wife's sister, ועל אשת אחיו, ve'al eshet
achiv, his brother's wife, ועל אשת אחי אביו, ve'al eshet achi aviv,
his aunt, his his father's brother's wife, okay, ועל הנדה, ve'al haniddah,
and a woman who is in נדה. niddah. All of these are
forbidden sexual acts, acts of intercourse that you get כרת. kares. And
the חידוש chiddush of the משנה mishna is that even though there's
the divine punishment of כרת, kares, you still can get מלקות malkus
if the עדים edim said don't do this, you'll get מלקות. malkus.
אלמנה לכהן גדול, almana l'kohen gadol, גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט. gerusha vechaluza
l'kohen hedyot. Now other people get מלקות, malkus, now that we're talking
about in the category of like forbidden acts of sex, you know,
a אלמנה almana a כהן גדול kohen gadol who marries a widow,
a גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט, gerusha vechaluza l'kohen hedyot, somebody who is
a a normal כהן kohen who has intercourse with a woman who
is divorced or is a חלוצה, chaluza, question about whether a חלוצה
chaluza is really דאורייתא d'oraisa or
not. So רש״י Rashi makes it sound like חלוצה chaluiza is דאורייתא
d'oraita and does get מלקות, malkus, but if it's a גרושה וחלוצה
grusha va-chaluiza coming together, you would only get one
because whatever they're... a חלוצה chaluiza is a type of a גרושה.
grusha. תוספות Tosfos takes the more standard approach in the גמרא Gemara
that a חלוצה chaluiza is a דרבנן, d'rabbanan, but you get מכת
מרדות. makas mardus. But if it's a... so that's sort of what
this is referring to. And with the simple sense of this משנה
mishnah obviously sounds like a חלוצה chaluiza is דאורייתא. d'oraita.
גרושה וחלוצה כהן הדיוט. grusha va-chaluiza kohen hedyot. ממזרת ונתינה לממזר. mamzeres
ve-nesina le-mamzer. And a ממזרת mamzeres or a נתין, nesin, somebody from
the גבעונים, Givonim, one of the שבעת עממים, shiv'as amim, for a
ישראל, Yisrael, for a normal ישראל. Yisrael. All these are simple לאווין,
lavin, they're not כרת, kareis, simple לאווין lavin bad sexual acts and
that you get מלקות. malkus. בת ישראל לנתין ולממזר, bas Yisrael le-nesin
u-le-mamzer, similarly if it is a Jewish woman to a נתין nesin
and a ממזר. mamzer. Alright, now not much of a חידוש chidush
there, I mean other than the חלוצה chaluiza discussion, those are all
simple לאווין, lavin, but the reason it's being taught is for the
next line of the משנה. mishnah. אלמנה וגרושה חייב עליה משום שני
שמות. almanah u-grusha chayav aleha mishum shtei shemos. If somebody is both
an אלמנה almanah and a גרושה grusha and a כהן גדול kohen
gadol has intercourse with this woman who both was widowed from husband
one, divorced from husband two, now this כהן גדול kohen gadol marries
her, has intercourse with her, then that's two separate לאווין lavin because
even though it's one act, it's two separate עבירות aveiros being done
in one act. However, גרושה וחלוצה אינו חייב אלא משום שם אחד
בלבד. grusha va-chaluiza eino chayav ela mishum shem echad bilvad. גרושה Grusha
and חלוצה, chaluiza, a חלוצה chaluiza is like a type of a
גרושה, grusha, woman who was separated from her husband, cut the connection,
the tie was severed, and that's really a type of a גרושה
grusha if you assume it's דאורייתא d'oraita or even if you assume
it's דרבנן d'rabbanan anyway, it's a subcategory of גרושה grusha and therefore
only one set of מלקות. malkus. Okay, so that's one category. הטמא
שאכל את הקודש והבא אל המקדש טמא, ha-tamei she-achal es ha-kodesh ve-ha-ba
el ha-mikdash tamei, somebody who is טמא tamei who eats קרבנות, korbanos,
or somebody who goes into a בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash when they
are טמא. tamei. ואוכל חלב ודם ונותר ופיגול, ve-ochel chelev ve-dam ve-nosar
u-pigul, and somebody who eats forbidden fat and blood and נותר, nosar,
a קרבן korban that was left over the right amount of time,
פיגול, pigul, a קרבן korban that was שחט shechted with an intent
to eat it at the wrong time, all of these, those all
of these are things that you are again categories of things that
you would get כרת kareis for and nevertheless you get מלקות malkus
if you are warned for מלקות. malkus. So again that's sort of
the חידוש chidush here about things that otherwise you would be getting
כרת. kareis.
וטמא, ve-tamei, oh I forgot the וטמא, ve-tamei, or if somebody eats
קרבנות korbanos that are טמא, tamei,
although that is not the כרת. kareis. Okay. והשוחט ומעלה בחוץ, ve-ha-shocheit
u-ma'aleh ba-chutz, somebody who שוחט shechts a קרבן korban or brings offers
up the entrails outside of the בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash
and fine,
והשוחט ומעלה בחוץ ואוכל חמץ בפסח, ve-ha-shocheit u-ma'aleh ba-chutz ve-ochel chametz ba-Pesach,
somebody who eats חמץ chametz on פסח, Pesach, והאוכל והעושה מלאכה ביום
כיפור, ve-ha-ochel ve-ha-oseh melacha be-Yom Kippur, somebody who eats or does מלאכה
melacha on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, so these again things that you're
חייב כרת chayav kareis and nevertheless if you're warned for מלקות malkus
you get מלקות. malkus. המפטם את השמן והמפטם את הקטורת, ha-mifatem es
ha-shemen ve-ha-mifatem es ha-ketores, if somebody compounds, makes the שמן המשחה, shemen
ha-mishchah, you're not allowed to make the שמן המשחה shemen ha-mishchah according
to the way the תורה Torah describes how it's made, or if
you make the
קטורת ketores the way the תורה Torah sort of says that it's
supposed to be made.
והסך בשמן המשחה, ve-ha-sach be-shemen ha-mishchah, or if somebody that actually takes
the actual anointing oil and puts it on their anoints it on
their flesh. All those cases you would get again מלקות malkus even
though they are
on the category of כרת. kareis. ואוכל נבילות וטריפות שקצים ורמשים. ve-ochel
neveilos u-treifos shekatzim u-remasim. Now we're dealing with things that are forbidden
things to eat and not sort of in the כרת kareis but
nevertheless they're being mentioned
here in this משנה. mishnah. Somebody who
eats נבילה, neveila, animal that died without being שחט, shechted, טריפה, treifa,
animal that was שחט shechted but had an interior wound, forbidden types
of bugs and rodents, all those things are prohibited with a לאו
lav and you get מלקות, malkus, not much of a חידוש chidush
there, but we'll sort of see one of like an issue for
why it was brought up at the end of this משנה. mishnah.
אכל טבל ומעשר ראשון שלא נטלה תרומתו, achal tevel u-ma'aser rishon she-lo
nitlah trumaso, let's say somebody ate טבל tevel or מעשר ראשון ma'aser
rishon that did not have the תרומה trumah taken from the מעשר
ראשון. ma'aser rishon. So all of those would be cases about again
type of
a very severe punishment because of the תרומה trumah that was in
the טבל, tevel, שלא נטלה
תרומתו, she-lo nitlah trumaso, ומעשר שני והקדש שלא נפדו, u-ma'aser sheni ve-hekdesh
she-lo nifdu, or מעשר שני ma'aser sheni or הקדש hekdesh that have
not been redeemed. All of those cases are
forbidden things that are forbidden to be eaten and you get מלקות.
malkus. כמה יאכל מן הטבל ויהא חייב? kama yochal min ha-tevel ve-yehei
chayav? How much would you eat and be חייב? chayav? רבי שמעון
אומר כל שהוא, Rabbi Shimon omer kol she-hu, even the tiniest amount,
which is probably, וחכמים אומרים, ve-Chachamim omrim, the Sages say, כזית. k'zayis.
No,
only a size of an olive, which is what we know. אמר
להם רבי שמעון אי אתה מודה לי באוכל נמלה שהוא חייב כל
שהוא שחייב? Amar lahem Rebbe Shimon i ata modeh li b'ochal nemalah
shehu chaiev kol shehu shechaiev? Don't you agree to me that if
you eat an ant, even if it's a tiny ant, that you'd
be חייב chaiev even though it wasn't the size of an olive?
So again this is probably why it mentions the one of the
reasons it mentions the שקצים ורמשים shekatzim u'remasim and said in this
משנה mishnah that everybody agrees okay why do they agree? אמרו לו
Amru lo yes מפני שהוא כבריתה mipnei shehu k'beriasah yes that we
do agree but that is an entire unit that's an entire ant
that was the way it was created you know that's whereas when
you're talking about eating טבל tevel eating grain you know that's just
like a quantity and therefore you need a certain amount of it
in order for it to be significant. A whole ant is significant
but with grain if it's all fungible it's all more or less
of the same thing you need a minimum amount you need a
כזית. k'zayis.
אמר להם Amar lahem he said back to them אף חיטה
אחת כבריתה Af chitah achas k'beriasah why isn't one you know one
grain why isn't one kernel also it's a natural thing? So and
therefore therefore I obligate you know say somebody is חייב chaiev even
if they eat just one kernel that also has a status of
a בריה biryah a full unit. Okay so we'll see about that
in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
חייבי כריתות קתני חייבי מיתות בית דין לא קתני. Chaievei krisos kasani
chaievei misos beis din lo kasani. So our משנה mishnah mentions things
that you get כרת kares for and maybe we'll discuss also מיתה
בידי שמים misah biyedei shamayim and to say that even though you
can get כרת kares for them or whatever you can get warned
and get מלקות. malkus. Okay but if somebody does something that you
would get that's punishable by death and instead they warn him hey
don't do that you'll get מלקות malkus don't be מחלל שבת m'chalel
Shabbos you'll get מלקות malkus presumably
from our משנה mishnah you would not get מלקות malkus right? Because
our משנה mishnah very clearly started with חייבי כריתות chaievei krisos and
ignored
חייבי מיתות. chaievei misos. So מתניתין מני רבי עקיבא היא Masnisin mani
Rebbe Akiva hi so this follows רבי עקיבא. Rebbe Akiva. Now we're
going to see an interesting debate about different possibilities about what happens
with מיתה misah and מלקות malkus and so on.
רבי עקיבא דתניא Rebbe Akiva d'tanya אחד חייבי כריתות ואחד חייבי מיתות
בית דין echad chaievei krisos v'echad chaievei misos beis din whether something
you would get כרת kares for or even if you would get
מיתה בית דין misah beis din for top of י"ג
עמוד ב' yud gimmel amud beis ישנו בכלל מלקות ארבעים. yeshno bichlal
malkus arbaim. You would get forty lashes. דברי רבי ישמעאל Divrei Rebbe
Yishmael that's what רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael says. Now
originally there's two obvious ways to read this. One is that if
they warned him you know
don't do that if you do it you'll get killed and you'll
get lashes that they could both give him lashes and then go
ahead and kill him. They could give him both right? So every
transgression is deserving of lashes and some can even more on top
of that they would even get executed but you know you can
get both for the same transgression. Okay that's one way of reading
it which is where the גמרא Gemara is going to start with.
The other way of reading it is no they didn't say if
you're מחלל שבת m'chalel Shabbos you'll get lashes and you'll get מיתה.
misah. They just said you'll get lashes the עדים eidim didn't understand
and רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Yishmael says you know what in that case
you can give him lashes. Okay but we're not talking that you're
going to give him both. But anyway we're starting with the understanding
that רבי ישמעאל Rebbe Ishmael is saying that you would give him
both. רבי עקיבא אומר חייבי כריתות ישנו בכלל מלקות ארבעים שאם עשו
תשובה בית דין של מעלה מוחלין להם. Rebbe Akiva omer chaievei krisos
yeshno bichlal malkus arbaim she'im asu teshuvah beis din shel maalah mochalin
lahem. When somebody does כרת kares you can give him lashes okay
because what's the normal problem about giving somebody two things? The problem
is you know you only it's there's a normal principle about כדי
רשעתו k'dei rishaso according to somebody's wickedness משום רשעה אחת אתה מחייבו
ואי אתה מחייבו משום שתי רשעיות. mishum rishah achas ata mechayvo v'i
ata mechayvo mishum shtei rishayus. You can only you know make somebody
liable for one act of of evil not for two. A principle
sometimes referred to as קים ליה בדרבה מיניה kim lei b'drabbah minei
there might be some slight differences between them but you don't punish
somebody twice for the same sin. Okay so רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva
says
מלקות malkus and מיתה misah you can't give him twice you can't
punish him both give him מלקות malkus and give him מיתה. misah.
But מלקות malkus and כרת kares you can give him מלקות malkus
because כרת kares he might not get because if he does תשובה
teshuvah God will forgive him. So since כרת kares he won't necessarily
get you're able to do מלקות malkus even though כרת kares is
there in the background. But you can't give מלקות malkus if you're
going to be giving him מיתה. misah. Okay שאם עשו תשובה בית
דין של מעלה מוחלין להם she'im asu teshuvah beis din shel maalah
mochalin lahem by כרת kares if they do תשובה teshuvah the heavenly
court forgives them. חייבי מיתות בית דין אינו בכלל מלקות ארבעים Chaievei
misos beis din eino bichlal malkus arbaim but if somebody does something
that you're deserving מיתה בית דין misah beis din you cannot get
מלקות malkus in that case. שאם עשו תשובה אין בית דין של
מטה מוחלין להם she'im asu teshuvah ein beis din shel mata mochalin
lahem even if you do תשובה teshuvah if somebody did the crime
they get executed it doesn't matter. תשובה Teshuvah is between you and
God it's not between you and the בית דין beis din and
how the בית דין beis din is going to punish you. Okay
so I mean we also learned in סנהדרין Sanhedrin that they got
to got him to do תשובה teshuvah before they executed him. So
there the problem you don't you can't you don't get punished twice
but כרת kares we're going to give you מלקות malkus that's not
punishing you twice you'll do תשובה teshuvah you won't get כרת. kares.
אינו בכלל מלקות ארבעים
שאם עשו תשובה אין בית דין של מטה מוחלין להם. Eino bichlal
malkus arbaim she'im asu teshuvah ein beis din shel mata mochalin lahem.
רבי יצחק אומר חייבי כריתות בכלל היו. Rebbe Yitzchak omer chaievei krisos
bichlal hayu. רבי יצחק Rebbe Yitzchak says you know what and some
that חייבי כריתות chaievei krisos normally were in the category of
so you know חייבי כריתות chaievei krisos was in the general category
of of מלקות. malkus. It's a לאו lav so of course by
every
לאו. lav. So okay, they started in that general
category, so בכלל היו. b'klal hayu. ולמה יצאת כרת באחותו, V'lamah yatzas
kareis b'achoso, so then why did the Torah when it speaks about
the, you know, man who sleeps with his sister he says he'll
get כרת? kareis? Now the Torah didn't have to say that, because
it says at the end כל אשר יעשה מכל התועבות האלה ונכרתו.
kol asher yaaseh mikol hato'eivos ha'eleh v'nichrasu. It mentions כרת kareis by
all the עריות. arayos. So why did it go out of its
way to specifically say כרת kareis by the case of sister? לדונו
בכרת ולא במלקות, Laduno b'chareis v'lo b'malkos, to tell you, and and
this is an example for everything else,
this עבירה, aveira, the only punishment you'll get for this is כרת.
kareis. There is no מלקות. malkos. And that then becomes a paradigm
that any חייב כרת, chayav kareis, the only punishment the Torah is
assigning it is כרת kareis and there is no מלקות. malkos. Okay,
so now we have all three possibilities. רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael says
you get both. רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says you only get מלקות.
malkos. And רבי יצחק Rebbi Yitzchak says there's no מלקות malkos for
חייבי כריתות. chayavei krisos. All three possibilities. Now let's go ahead and
analyze this. מאי טעמא דרבי ישמעאל? Mai taama d'Rebbi Yishmael? What's the
reasoning of רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael that says you can get both?
דכתיב אם לא תשמור לעשות את כל דברי התורה הזאת, Dichsiv im
lo sishmor laasos es kol divrei haTorah hazos, if you don't observe
all these words of this Torah. וכתיב, Uchsiv, and then it says
והפלא ה' את מכותך, v'hifla Hashem es makosecha, God will make your,
you know, increase your smitings. הפלאה זו איני יודע מה היא, Hafla'ah
zu eini yodeia mah hi, I don't know what this הפלאה hafla'ah
word like פלא, pela, like wondrous, you know, will be the way
in which you'll get punished by God. But the גמרא Gemara is
going to read it like a, like a homonym. כשהוא אומר והפילו
השופט, K'shehu omer v'hipilo hashofet, the judge will cast him down, you
know, and that's כדי רשעתו במספר kdei rishaso b'mispar and he'll give
him lashes. ארבעים יכנו, Arba'im yakenu, והכהו לפניו, v'hikahu l'fanav, הוי אומר
הפלאה זו מלקות היא. Hevei omer hafla'ah zu malkos hi. It's getting
מלקות. malkos. Okay, so the Torah says את כל דברי התורה הזאת.
es kol divrei haTorah hazos. If anybody who doesn't do anything, והפלא
ה' את מכותך, v'hifla Hashem es makosecha, to tell you basically that
any לאו lav you're going to get מלקות malkos for.
וכתיב, v'chsiv, and then it says אם לא תשמור לעשות את כל
דברי התורה הזאת. im lo sishmor laasos es kol divrei haTorah hazos.
All right, so anything you'll get מלקות malkos for, even something that's
חייב מיתת בית דין. chayav misas beis din. That's where רבי ישמעאל
Rebbi Yishmael learns it from. אי הכי, Ei hachi, says the גמרא,
Gemara, חייבי עשה נמי? chayavei asei nami? So why are you limiting
yourself
to a לאו תעשה? lav taaseh? If you don't do anything you'll
get מלקות. malkos. Let's include also if you passively don't do an
עשה. asei. No, אם לא תשמור כתיב, im lo sishmor kesiv, because
it says if you don't observe to do all of this Torah.
וכי רבי אבין אמר רבי אילעא, V'chi Rebbi Avin amar Rebbi Ila'a,
like רבי אבין Rebbi Avin in the name of רבי אילעא Rebbi
Ila'a says. דאמר רבי אבין אמר רבי אילעא כל מקום שנאמר השמר
פן ואל, D'amar Rebbi Avin amar Rebbi Ila'a kol makom shene'emar hishamer
pen v'al, guard yourself, lest, don't, אינו אלא לאו תעשה. eino ela
lav taaseh. That means don't do something. So so you're supposed to
be שומר לעשות, shomer laasos, you're supposed to watch yourself
and you know to to not do something. And you were לא
תשמור, lo sishmor, you didn't, you know, you didn't abide by that
and you actively violated something that you were supposed to be prescribed
against doing. That's how we're reading it. אינו אלא לאו תעשה. Eino
ela lav taaseh. אי הכי, Ei hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, לאו
שאין בו מעשה נמי? lav she'ein bo maaseh nami? So okay, so
then why do we still, why are we limiting מלקות malkos if
we're learning it from this פסוק אם לא תשמור לעשות? pasuk im
lo sishmor laasos? Let's give you מלקות malkos if you just passively
transgress a לאו. lav. No, לעשות כתיב, laasos kesiv, to do. Okay,
but it's funny, it doesn't say like your עבירה aveira was in
doing, you weren't שומר shomer from doing what you were supposed to
be doing. But anyway, we're reading from the לעשות laasos to mean
actively if you actively violate. So the גמרא Gemara says לאו הניתק
לעשה נמי? lav hanitak l'asei nami? So okay, give מלקות malkos again.
You're reading it from this very general פסוק. pasuk. Give מלקות malkos
even for somebody who does a לאו lav that has an עשה
asei that can fix it. Okay, we'll see about those later. So
the גמרא Gemara says no,
לעשות נמי, laasos nami, דומיא דלאו דחסימה. dumya d'lav d'chasimah. No, no,
no, because in the end it goes to the פסוק pasuk about
you
know והפילו השופט והכהו לפניו. v'hipilo hashofet v'hikahu l'fanav. And that פרשה
parsha about getting מלקות malkos is juxtaposed to לא תחסום שור בדישו
lo sachsom shor b'disho about not to muzzle an ox while it's
threshing. And that's the paradigm of what things get מלקות malkos from.
It has to be similar to the prohibition about not muzzling the
ox. So it has to be a לאו תעשה. lav taaseh. It
has to be you actively violate, you muzzled, and it has to
be something that doesn't have, is not ניתק לעשה, nitak l'asei, cannot
be fixed by an עשה. asei. So that's where we learn what
you get מלקות malkos from. So the גמרא Gemara says okay,
so השתא דאתית להכי, hashta d'asis l'hachi, כולהו נמי דומיא דלאו דחסימה.
kulhu nami dumya d'lav d'chasimah. Oh, so if that's true, so why
do you have to start me from this whole פסוק pasuk of
והפלא ה' את מכותך? v'hifla Hashem es makosecha? This is an answer,
not a question, but it's like let's just say, how do you
know you get מלקות? malkos? From the פסוק pasuk that everybody agrees
that you get מלקות, malkos, the פסוק pasuk about והפילו השופט והכהו
לפניו. v'hipilo hashofet v'hikahu l'fanav. Anything that's similar to the לאו lav
of חסימה chasimah of muzzling, and that would include things that are
prohibitions that you would get מיתת בית דין misas beis din for.
Okay, there's, I mean, yes, the muzzling is not מיתת בית דין,
misas beis din, but again that's not excluded from that paradigm. Okay,
so in the end, we just settled back on the פסוק Pasuk
we normally start with about getting מלקות, Malkos, which is והפילו השופט,
Ve-hipilo ha-shofet, and it's juxtaposed to the לאו Lav of חסימה, Chasima,
but maybe the פסוק Pasuk that says את כל דברי, Es kol
divrei, which has a broad sense from that רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael
is learning to include even things that you would get מיתה Misa
for, you also get מלקות Malkos for. And we will continue tomorrow
to see רבי עקיבא'ס Rebbi Akiva's response that, you know, you don't
apply this when it is something that you don't get two punishments
and how sort of רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael would deal with that.
Okay, so to be continued tomorrow.